Guide to the Radio Haiti Papers, circa 1934-2003, bulk 1968-2003 RL.11499
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Human Rights, 1977-2003
  - Children's Rights, 1986-2003
    - General, 1986-2003; 4 folders (Box 102)
      Radio Haiti materials on children's rights, including child trafficking, restavèk, Lafanmi Selavi, adoption and trafficking of children (including ex-consul of Haiti in France Jacqueline Jospitre's allegations that the consulate was engaging in corruption and child trafficking), the closure of Village SOS orphanage, children and justice, children living on the street, chilen's health, UNICEF activities, and other topics. Organizations represented include Haitian organizations (including Centre de Promotion des Droits Humains, Ligue de Defense des Droits de l'Enfance, Centre d'Education Spéciale), and international organizations (Minnesota Lawyers for Human Rights).
  - Commemorations, 1988-1998
    - 40th anniversary Universal Declaration of Human Rights, 1988; 1 folder (Box 101)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about Haitian commemorations of the fortieth anniversary of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights in December 1988.
    - 50th anniversary Universal Declaration of Human Rights, 1998; 1 folder (Box 101)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about Haitian commemorations of the fiftieth anniversary of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights in December 1998.
  - Disability, 1996-2002
    - General, 1996-2002; 1 folder (Box 102)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the rights of people with disabilities. Includes the Société Haïtienne d'Aide aux Aveugles (SHAA).
  - Haitian organizations, 1978-2003
    - Centre de Promotion des Droits Humains, 1987-1990; 1 folder (Box 102)
      See also: Lafontant Joseph assassination
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials by and about the Centre de Promotion des Droits Humains (later the Centre Lafontant Joseph de Promotion des Droits Humains). Includes letters from Lafontant Joseph.
    - Centre oecuménique des droits de l'homme, 1987-2002; 1 folder (Box 102)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials by and about the Centre oecuménique des droits de l'homme and its director, Jean-Claude Bajeux. Includes materials about the rights of Haitian immigrants abroad.
    - CHADEL, 1986-1991; 1 folder (Box 102)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials by and about CHADEL (Centre Haïtien des Droits et Libertés) under executive director Jean Jacques Honorat.
    - CHREHDU, 1996-1997; 1 folder (Box 102)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the Commission haïtienne pour le respect des droits humains (CHREDHU) and its activities.
    - Fondation 30 Septembre, 1997-2003; 1 folder (Box 102)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials by and about Fondation 30 Septembre under the leadership of Lovinsky Pierre-Antoine. Includes advocacy for victims of the 1991 coup d'état (including the Raboteau massacre and the homes burned by FRAPH in Cité Soleil), several sit-ins, and other subjects.
    - L.A.P.P.H., 1986-1998; 1 folder (Box 103)
      Radio Haiti materials and L.A.P.P.H. materials from the first year of the L.A.P.P.H. (Ligue des Anciens Prisonniers Politiques Haïtiens), including founding documents, the August 1986 human rights seminar. Radio Haiti scripts on the activities of the L.A.P.P.H., including L.A.P.P.H's denunciation of Duvalierists' impunity, including Albert "Ti Boule" Pierre; threats to member; arrests of members; internal divisions and revocations within L.A.P.P. H., etc. L.A.P.P.H.-produced materials (including press releases, open letters, reports). Includes Duvalierism, army repression, CNG, arrests, internal divisions within L.A.P.P.H. Four copies of Le Militant.
    - M.J.P.D.A. report, 1978; 1 folder (Box 103)
      See also: CIDH; Duvalierism and Macoutism
      The Mouvman Jè Patriyot Démokrat Aiysyin's report submitted to the CIDH, in which they allege that the Duvalier regime's pretense of liberalization is just that, and that the regime continues to commit human rights violations.
    - NCHR, 1987-2002; 3 folders (Box 103)
      See also: POHDH; Human Rights Watch
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials (mainly press releases and open letters) by and about NCHR, first as the National Coalition for Haitian Refugees and later as the National Coalition for Haitian Rights. Includes materials on the rights of Haitian refugees in the United States, the justice system and the Police Nationale d'Haïti, insecurity, prison conditions, and several cases of human rights violations. Includes open letters from NCHR director Michael Hooper about the human rights situation in Haiti in the late 1980s. Includes reactions to threats against the director of NCHR's Haiti office, Pierre Espérance. Also includes several issues of newsletter "Haiti Insight." reports co-authored by NCHR and Human Rights Watch and collaborations with POHDH. (Note: NCHR was an international organization with headquarters in both New York and Port-au-Prince. However, because they worked only on Haitian issues and most of the materials in the Radio Haiti archive concerns their Haiti offices and staff, it has been categorized as a Haitian organization.)
    - NCHR and POHDH, threats, 2001; 1 folder (Box 103)
      Open letters to President Jean-Bertrand Aristide from several human rights organizations concerning death threats against Pierre Espérance and Vilès Alizar of NCHR and Serge Bordenave and Jean Simon Saint Hubert of POHDH in November 2001.
    - POHDH (1 of 2), 1996-2002; 1 folder (Box 103)
      See also: NCHR
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials by and about the Plate-Forme des Organisations Haïtiennes des Droits Humains (POHDH). Includes commemorations of human rights violations, reports and investigations into human rights violations and violence around Haiti (including a report co-authored by POHDH and Radio Haïti-Inter about events in Quartier Morin in March 2000). Includes collaborations with NCHR and CIDH.
    - POHDH (2 of 2), 1996-2002; 1 folder (Box 104)
  - International organizations, 1977-2002
    - Amnesty International, 1986-2002; 2 folders (Box 104)
      See also: Duvalierism and Macoutism; Jean Dominique assassination; Attempted assassination of Michèle Montas
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials. Amnesty International reports and publications on disappearances under the Duvalier regime, prison conditions, torture, arrests, and other human rights violations. Letters from Amnesty International letter-writing campaign denouncing human rights abuses by the CNG, addressed to Prosper Avril and others. Amnesty International's annual reports and press releases, discussing the human rights situation after the coup years, the Jean Dominique assassination, prison, Haiti-Dominican relations, and other topics.
    - CIDH, 1977-2002; 5 folders (Box 104)
      See also: OAS; M.J.P.D.A report
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the Cour interaméricaine des droits de l'homme/Inter-American Court of Human Rights (CIDH) of the Organization of American States. Includes reports on the human rights situation in Haiti in 1977-1978, the 1988 "Rapport sur la situation des droits de l'homme en Haïti"; and CIDH reactions to the human rights situation in Haiti in the democratic era.
    - Human Rights Watch, 1995-2001; 1 folder (Box 105)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials by and about Human Rights Watch activities, including demands for the government of Panama to extradite Raoul Cédras and Philippe Biamby.
    - Lawyers Committee for Human Rights, 1990-1991; 1 folder (Box 105)
      Reports and open letters from the Lawyers Committee for Human Rights concerning the human rights situation in Haiti in 1990-1991, before the September 1991 coup d'état.
    - United Nations, 1978; 1996-2002; 2 folders (Box 105)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials by and about the United Nations' human rights activities in Haiti, particularly the joint UN-OAS Mission Civile Internationale en Haïti (MICIVIH) and the visit of consultants Louis Joinet and Adama Dieng.
  - Refugees and Repatriations, 1980-2003
    - "The Political Economy of the Haitian Refugee Crisis," Jean-Jacques Honorat, 1982; 1 folder (Box 105)
      Jean-Jacques Honorat's May 1982 analysis of the Haitian refugee crisis.
    - Belize repatriation plan, 1982-1983; 1 folder (Box 105)
      External materials about the US government's plans to resettle Haitian refugees as "homesteaders" in Belize.
    - Cayo Lobos, 1980; 1 folder (Box 105)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the Haitian refugees who washed up on Cayo Lobos, Bahamas and the subsequent contestations over which government would be responsible.
    - Detention - gynecomastia, 1982; 1987; 1 folder (Box 105)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the epidemic of gynecomastia (abnormal breast growth) among Haitian men in US detention facilities, and the 1987 lawsuit by these men against INS.
    - Dominican Republic, 1995-2003; 2 folders (Box 105)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about repatriations and deportations of Haitians and people of Haitian descent from the Dominican Republic. Includes policy by the Dominican government, advocacy by GARR (Groupe d'Appui aux Rapatriés et Réfugiés), policy and actions by the Office Nationale de le Migration (ONM) and the International Organization for Migration (IOM).
    - Migrants at Sea, 1986-1989; 1 folder (Box 105)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about migrants at sea (so-called "boat people"), including repatriations and shipwrecks. Includes the ships Santa Clara (1986) Dieu Ci Bon (1989) both of which sank in Cuban waters. Includes reports and press on the Haitian refugee crisis, by Haitian organizations, Red Cross, Haitian government, Bahamas government, US embassy, among others.
    - Migrants at Sea, 1990-1991; 1 folder (Box 105)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about refugees at sea (co-called "boat people") including repatriations and interceptions by US and Bahamian authorities. Includes reactions from NCHR, the Centre Lafontant Joseph de Promotion des Droits Humains, FNCD, and other Haitian human rights groups and political parties.
    - Migrants at Sea, 1995-2003; 4 folders (Box 106)
      See also: International relations; Immigration; Maritime accidents
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about migrants at sea (so-called "boat people"), including repatriations and deportations, shipwrecks, refugee rights, reintegration of repatriated people into Haitian society, former Guantanamo detainees, immigration policy. Includes Haitian people in or attempting to reach the USA, the Bahamas, Providenciales, Turks and Caicos, and other countries, as well as smaller amounts of materials about Cuban refugees. Florida Rural Legal Services of Miami's "Not In Their Best Interest: A Report on the US Government's Forcible Repatriation of Guantánamo's Unaccompanied Haitian Children" (1995).
    - Migrants at Sea: other printed materials, 1980-1984; 1 folder (Box 106)
      Essays, press releases, speeches, reports, and other printed material on the Haitian refugee crisis. Includes Leslie Péan, Max Dominique, Jean Claude Bajeux of the CEDH, the Haitian Refugee Center in Miami, the Haitian Embassy, among others. Also includes fliers for demonstrations for Haitian rights, bumper sticker, and other items.
    - Migrants at Sea: USA, news, 1981-1984; 1 folder (Box 106)
      See also: Immigration; Maritime accidents
      News clippings and articles collected by Jean Dominique during exile in New York, concerning seafaring refugees ("boat people") from Haiti trying to flee to the United States. Includes drownings and capsized boats (including two in October 1981), the the US government's double standard vis-à-vis Haitian refugees (who were considered economic migrants) and Cuban refugees (who were considered political asylum-seekers), conditions in detention centers such as Krome and Fort Allen. News sources include the New York Times, Le Nouvelliste, Le Nouveau Monde, USA Today, Amsterdam News, Haïti Observateur, Libération, Le Monde, Newsweek.
  - Women's Rights, 1982-2003
    - General, 1982-2003 (bulk 1986-2003; 4 folders (Box 107)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about women's rights. Includes information on grassroots women's organizations, including SOFA, Fanm Je Klere (FAJEK), Kay Fanm, Enfofanm, Fanm Yola, Fanm Dayiti, and Lig Pouvwa Fanm; rural women and land reform; the rights of female prisoners; International Women's Day (March 8) and the International Day for the Elimination of Violence Against Women (November 25); violence against women, women's health, and rape (especially the case of Natacha Jean-Jacques, a teenager who was raped and impregnated in prison); government decrees; reports from international organizations; and Jean-Claude Duvalier's 1982 decree on the status of women.
    - Ministère à la Condition Féminine, 1995-1999; 1 folder (Box 107)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials on the activities and politics of the Ministère à la Condition Féminine. External materials include press releases and publications by the Ministry, communication from grassroots groups, and press.
- Impunity and Dictatorship, 1957-2003
  - Army, 1973-2001 (bulk 1987-2001)
    - Association des Vétérans Militaires Haïtiens, 1987-1988; 1 folder (Box 108)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials on the Associations des Vétérans Militaires Haïtiens' denunciations of the army's actions.
    - Biamby mutiny, 1989; 1 folder (Box 108)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials on Philippe Biamby's attempted overthrow of Prosper Avril in April 1989.
    - Chefs de section, repression (1-4 of 6), 1988-1991; 4 folders (Box 108)
      See also: Peasant movements; Land conflicts; Massacres
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the repression of peasant farmers in rural areas of the country by chefs de section (section chiefs, or local sheriffs), and calls to reform the chefs de section system. Many of these chefs de sections were former Macoutes. Includes repression throughout the Haitian countryside, including the Artibonite (particularly the Bas-Artibonite) including Saint-Marc, Verettes, Pérodin, and Saint-Michel-de-l'Attalaye; Mirebalais; Labadie, Limbé; Petit-Goâve; Grand-Bois; and elsewhere. Includes reactions from several grassroots peasants' rights groups, including Solidarite Peyizan Ayisyen (SOPA) and Tèt Kole Ti Peyizan Ayisyen, the latter of which published a report entitled "Chèf seksyon: yon sistèm ki merite elimine." Also includes many handwritten petitions from peasant groups throughout Haiti.
    - Chefs de section, repression (5-6 of 6), 1988-1991; 2 folders (Box 109)
    - Chefs de section: Onondieu Paul, 1995; 1 folder (Box 109)
      See also: Land conflicts; Peasant movements
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the arrest and charges against former chef de section Onondieu Paul of Marchand Dessalines, including dossier by MITPA (Mouvman Inite Ti Peyizan Ayisyen).
    - Col. Jean-Claude Paul, 1987-1989; 1 folder (Box 109)
      See also: Drugs
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about colonel and accused cocaine smuggler Jean-Claude Paul, his death by poisoning, and the arrest of his ex-wife, Mireille Délinois.
    - Disappearance of Vladimir David, 1986; 1 folder (Box 109)
      Open letter from Marie Thérèse Dupervil, the mother of eighteen--year-old Vladimir David, who was arrested and disappeared by the army on 7 November 1986.
    - Dissolution of Army, 1995-2001; 1 folder (Box 109)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the dissolution of the Haitian army, claims and demands by ex-military, disarmament of former military, and safeguards against the army's return. Includes the Haitian senate's 1996 resolution, activities by the Fondation 30 Septembre, and other materials.
    - General, 1986-1990; 2 folders (Box 109)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the army in general, including reforms and dismissals, official communiqués and declarations from the Grand Quartier Général, celebrations of 18 November. Also includes Dany Toussaint's 1987 interview with Ekran magazine.
    - General, 1990-1991; 1 folder (Box 109)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the army in general, including reforms and dismissals, official communiqués and declarations from the Grand Quartier Général.
    - Incidents and abuses, 1987-1991; 2 folders (Box 110)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about violent incidents and abuses involving the army throughout Haiti. Includes the Corps des Léopards.
    - Jean-Claude Duvalier government, 1973-1984; 1 folder (Box 110)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the Haitian army during the presidency of Jean-Claude Duvalier. Includes reforms, the trial of Claude Rémy (1978), recruitment and graduation from the military academy (including the class of 1980, which included some of the perpetrators of the Raboteau massacre), and other topics.
    - Justice and court martials, 1986-1990; 1 folder (Box 110)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about court martials and trials of military officers and soldiers. Includes the trials of Robesse Métellus, Jean Brunel Goby, Michel Boncy, Antoine C. Métellus, and others charged with violent crimes or corruption. Also includes the FAd'H's rebuttal of accusations against Jean Claude Paul, Claude Raymond, Williams Régala, Franck Romain.
    - Mutinies and attempted coups d'état, 1988-1990; 1 folder (Box 110)
      See also: Biamby mutiny; Justice and court martials; Avril
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about mutinies and attempted coups d'état. Includes the October 1988 attempt by Samuel Jérémie, Patrick Beauchard, and Pierre Cherubin to overthrow Prosper Avril, the April 1989 coup attempt by the Corps des Léopards against Prosper Avril, and mutinies against commanders elsewhere in Haiti.
    - Police and arrests, 1987-1991; 1 folder (Box 110)
      See also: Rule of Law
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about the police (including the Police de Port-au-Prince) and arrests by the police. Includes the conflict between Père Sicot (Occide Jean) and residents of Kenscoff, the eviction of squatters from the Bennett home in Péguyville, several communiqués from police chief Georges Valcin, CNG decree.
    - Règlements Généraux des Forces Armées d'Haïti, 1987; 1 folder (Box 110)
      "Règlements Généraux des Forces Armées d'Haïti" published by Le Moniteur on 13 July 1987. Also includes the message from Generals Henri Namphy and Williams Régala on 17 July 1987 about the army, in which they describe it as an insititution that maintains peace.
    - Sept. 17 coup d'état, reforms, 1988-1990; 3 folders (Box 110)
      Radio Haiti materials on divisions within the Haitian army, the 17 September 1988 coup d'état in which Prosper Avril overthrew Henri Namphy, and subsequent efforts to reform the army. Also includes OP 17 Septembre. Reactions from political parties, unions, and civil society groups, including KID, PDCH, CATH, FENEH, ANOP, KONAKOM, and others.
  - Assassinations and Murders, 1982-2003
    - Life and death of Richard Brisson, 1982-1998; 1 folder (Box 111)
      Radio Haiti remembrances of Richard Brisson on the anniversary of his death (by Michèle Montas). Flier from Brisson's May 1981 performance of "Journal d'un in New York. Program from the March 1987 memorial concert for Brisson at Sainte-Trinité. Reflections on the memorial concert by Hénec Titus and Madeleine Paillère. External media sources (Rolling Stone, Haïti Demain, Haïti Progrès, Le Miroir, L'Événement, La Nouvelle Haïti Tribune, Le Petit Samedi Soir, Le Point, Le Monde) on the January 1982 invasion of Ile-de-la-Tortue, organized by Bernard Sansaricq, in which Richard Brisson was killed, and on commemorations of Brisson's death. Official government press (Le Nouveau Monde) on the Ile-de-la-Tortue invasion, describing the executions of Brisson and his comrades as deaths in combat. Also contains Radio Haiti materials relating to the arrest of former judge Luckner Pierre in connection with the 1982 death of Brisson and the 1987 Jean Rabel massacre. (Haïti Demain also contains writings on corruption at the Minoterie d'Haïti and Jeune Haïti.)
    - Lafontant Joseph assassination, 1986-1998; 2 folders (Box 111)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials including news, press releases, declarations, reactions, and commemorations relating to the assassination of lawyer and human rights advocate Lafontant Joseph, director of the Centre de Promotion des Droits Humains.
    - Charlot Jacquelin arrest and disappearance, 1986-2002, bulk 1986-1988; 2 folders (Box 111)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the 1986 arrest, imprisonment, disappearance, and death of Charlot Jacquelin, a young activist from Cité Soleil and teacher with the Mission Alpha literacy campaign. Radio Haiti Materials are primarily from 1986 and 1987. External materials include tributes to Jacquelin, protests and declarations by grassroots groups, Mission Alpha, and the Ministry of Education. External materials are from 1986 to 1988.
    - Attempted assassination of priests at Freycineau, 1987-1988; 1 folder (Box 111)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the 1987 attempted assassination of five activist priests, Jean-Bertrand Aristide, Antoine Adrien, Jean-Marie Vincent, William Smarth, and Canadian priest Joseph Berger, at Freycineau. External materials include news, press release from the Ministry of Information, and open letter from other priests from Jérémie.
    - Louis Eugène Athis assassination, 1987-1988; 2 folders (Box 111)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the assassination of Louis Eugène Athis, founder of the MODELH-PRDH political party, on August 2, 1987. Includes reactions from several other political parties.
    - Yves Volel assassination, 1987-1998, bulk 1987-1989; 3 folders (Box 111)
      Includes Radio Haiti scripts and external materials (both pre- and post-assassination) relating to the 13 October 1987 assassination of presidential candidate Yves Volel. External materials include materials relating to an earlier attempt on Volel's life; a derogatory open letter to Volel from Duvalierist presidential candidate Edouard Francisque; press, declarations, and reactions to the assassination by the CEP, political parties, and grassroots groups; documents relating to the funeral proceedings; commemorations of the anniversary of the assassination.
    - Luc B. Innocent assassination, 1988; 1 folder (Box 112)
      External materials (news, Ministry of the Interior, MUR) on the death of Luc B. Innocent, of the Mouvement d'Union Révolutionnaire (MUR), in a confrontation with the army at Fonds-Verrettes.
    - Serge Villard and Jean-Marie Montès assassination, 1990; 3 folders (Box 112)
      See also: Ertha Pascal Trouillot
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials on the 1990 attack on the Conseil d'État, which killed legislator Serge Villard and union leader Jean-Marie Montès. External materials include news, press releases and declarations from government and civil society organizations, and the Conseil d'État's bulletin dedicated to the memory of Villard.
    - Mireille Durocher Bertin assassination, 1995-1996; 1 folder (Box 112)
      See also: Elections, CEP (for CEP's statement on Durocher Bertin's assassination)